<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saintship no ground of soveraignty, or, A treatise tending to prove, that the saints, barely considered as such, ought not to govern by Edw. Bagshaw ...</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11992365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11992365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52043</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52043)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 80:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saintship no ground of soveraignty, or, A treatise tending to prove, that the saints, barely considered as such, ought not to govern by Edw. Bagshaw ...</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saints --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52043:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52043:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SAINTSHIP No ground of <hi>SOVERAIGNTY:</hi> OR A TREATISE Tending to prove, That the SAINTS, barely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as ſuch, ought not to GOVERN.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edw: Bagſhaw,</hi> Student of <hi>Ch: Ch:</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device: the arms of the University of Oxford (McKerrow 427)</figDesc>
               <head>ACADEMIA OXONIESIS</head>
               <q>SAP<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>IEN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TIA ET FELI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>CIT<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ATIS</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxford,</hi> Printed by <hi>H: Hall,</hi> Printer to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, for <hi>T. Robinſon.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52043:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52043:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable <hi>JOHN DORMER</hi> Eſq; A Member of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the manner of my Life and nature of my Studies doth lead me to affect a more then ordinary Retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Privacy, yet I neither am, nor ought to be ſo great a ſtranger to the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Providence amongſt us, as not to take notice what great things it hath pleaſed God of late to doe for this Nation; if not by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating our hopes, yet at leaſt by preventing our fears, and bringing us within ſome nearer view of Settlement: Whileſt others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are taken up with celebrating the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and magnifying the means of our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance: I have a little made it my buſineſſe to ſearch into the cauſe of our Danger; which
<pb facs="tcp:52043:3"/>if once rightly ſtated, will be a direction for our preſent Senators, to ſecure themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Rock, on which the Ship of the <hi>COMMON-WEALTH</hi> hath almoſt been ruined. And herein there was no need of any long ſtudy; for who does not ſee, that the too free venting of all ſorts of Opinions, and that by all ſorts of men, how ignorant and unconcerned ſoever, will, if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, for ever keep us a Divided, and conſequently, make us an Unſetled People? Amongſt thoſe many Principles, which are now let looſe upon us, (to exerciſe the Faith and Patience of this laſt Age) there is none that I know of, which doth either more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately conduce to the ruine of all Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or had a greater influence, in the pretences at leaſt, of the Actors, upon our late unwarrantable Diſturbances, then this which I have here endeavored to confute. For let this once be granted, that our Saviour is a Temporal Prince, and that onely thoſe have a right to Govern who have by Faith an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in him, preſently a door is opened to all manner of Rebellion and Treaſon; nay, there can be no ſuch Crimes in the World, if Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="tcp:52043:3"/>and a deſign to advance our Saviours Kingdom, be once made the pretence to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize them. Indeed the conſequents are ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and horrid, and the remembrance of <hi>Munſter</hi> Affairs (which were acted by the ſame ſpirit) ſo freſh,
<note place="margin">Sleid. lib. 10.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, that it might almoſt ſeem needleſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor any other confutation, then a bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of that Story.</p>
            <p>But Sir, that I may take here that liberty, which you have hitherto always indulged me, of ſpeaking my thoughts: I never yet looked upon that way of confuting an Error, which the <hi>Arminian</hi> Writers do uſually tread in, to be either Rational or Convincing; I mean, by urging the Inconveniences and ill Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Doctrine we diſpute againſt: For it is one Queſtion, What is true? and another, What is convenient? and after all thoſe Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Inferences, wherewith men ſeek to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright unwary and unobſerving Readers, yet this will be an eternal Axiome, That truth is truth, let the conſequences be what they will; and the more harſh and repugnant any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, if plainly revealed, ſeems unto Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reaſon, the greater is our Faith, and the
<pb facs="tcp:52043:4"/>more ſignall our Obedience, if we notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding do ſubmit unto and embrace it. In pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution therefore of this Deſign (which I have laid down to my ſelf, as the onely ſatisfactory way of deciding all Controverſies in Divinity) I have not inquired ſo much how dangerous, or how deſtructive and ruinous the contrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is, as <hi>how it is written;</hi> and ſo have proceeded by direct proof, to ſhew that their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion who would have Soveraignty founded upon that bottom, is utterly unſcriptural; for that it is unreaſonable, I think none makes any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And therefore I hope this Treatiſe may be uſeful for thoſe <hi>who erre, not knowing the Scriptures,</hi> and following the ſound of words, have not leiſure, nor perhaps ability, to look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſenſe of them. Had I conſulted my own credit, I might have made this Diſcourſe more plauſible, by filling up my Pages with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of ancient Writers; but I purpoſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, both becauſe thoſe, for whoſe ſakes I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſh it, are not acquainted with any thing of Chriſtianity, more then their Engliſh Bibles do inſtruct them in; and likewiſe becauſe I thought it needleſs, having ſo much of Divine Authority for my Text, to croud humane Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb facs="tcp:52043:4"/>into the Margin; ſince ſuch mixtures doe uſually make a good Cauſe ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>Sir, Whatever it is, I humbly preſent it to you, and doubt not, how rude and inartificial ſoever it ſeems, but it will finde entertainment among thoſe who love ſeaſonable Truths, if you pleaſe firſt to honor it with your Acceptance: Whoſe Piety, Prudence, Integrity, and Zeal for your Countrys Liberty and Welfare, have as much advanced you in the Eſteem and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſober and unprejudiced men, as your many perſonal Favours in the Heart and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obliged, and moſt humbly devoted Servant,</hi> Edw: Bagſhaw.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ch: Ch:</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan. 26. 1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52043:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52043:5"/>
            <head>SAINTSHIP No ground of <hi>SOVERAIGNTY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntending to prove out of Scripture that the Saints ought not to governe the earth, in that ſenſe which is now by ſome contended for, I ſhall take for the ground of my diſcourſe thoſe words of our Saviour to <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.36</note> when he ſaid, <hi>My kingdom is not of this world,</hi> which words are very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, whether we regard the Perſon who, the Time when, or the Manner how they were ſpoken.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52043:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. For the Perſon who ſpoke them, it was no leſſe then our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Chriſt,</hi> each of whoſe ſpeeches, how occaſionall ſoever, ought to be unto us ſo many Precepts and Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to Duty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Time when they were ſpoken, it was juſt then when he was taking his leave of Earth,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13.</note> that <hi>he witneſſed before Pilate a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion,</hi> of which, this Aſſertion is the greateſt Part: ſo that if the words of dying men do uſe to make the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt impreſſions, then ought theſe of our Saviour, even upon that account, to quicken our Attention.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for the Manner how they were ſpoken, it was not only after a Reſolved and ſeemingly Obſtinate ſilence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc.</hi> 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>in ſo much as the Governour marveiled,</hi> but in direct Anſwer to <hi>Pilate's</hi> Queſtion, who was very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know, whether our Saviour was <hi>King</hi> or not; ſo that our Saviour's Purpoſed and Poſitive diſavowing any Temporall or Earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52043:6"/>his redoubling this Aſſertion in the following part of the verſe, <hi>My Kingdome is not from hence;</hi> his repeating and inſiſting upon it againe in the next verſe, as a <hi>bearing witneſſe to the Truth,</hi> ought to convince us that our Saviour was in earneſt, and therefore the matter is very Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable.</p>
            <p>If therefore we put all this toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, viz. the Authority of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Exigence of the time, joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thoſe Vehement and Reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Circumſtances, wherewith theſe words are Accompanied, we may from thence conclude, that they containe in them a leſſon, of more then ordinary concernment to us.</p>
            <p>For the more Full and cleare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.47</note> we muſt have recourſe to one of the foregoing Chapters, where we find that the <hi>chiefe Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of our Saviours Miracles, and of that great Reſort of Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto him, (which were enough
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52043:7"/>at any time, if micheivouſly inclined to raiſe a Commotion in the State,) upon this they preſently called a <hi>Councell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Σανέδρι<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ον.</note> or, according to the Greeks, a <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> which was the Supreme and Higheſt Court of Judicature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>lib.</hi> 4.</note> and unto which, if <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> doth rightly informe us, even their Kings were Accountable. Here being convened they fall to debate about the beſt Expedient, how to cut our Saviour off, for fear their to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerating one, who was Publickly voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for King,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.5. &amp; <hi>Job.</hi> 18.</note> and ſo ſtiled likewiſe by himſelfe, (though in a far other ſenſe then they interpreted it) might be conſtrued by the <hi>Romanes</hi> (to whom the <hi>Jewes</hi> were at that time Tributaries) as a deſigne to ſhake off their Yoke, and thereby provoke them to an utter extirpation of the Jewiſh Policy, which untill then, notwithſtanding their Conqueſt, they had in great meaſure preſerved Entire. Thus therefore we find them Argue, <hi>If we let him alone, all men
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52043:7"/>will believe on him,
<note place="margin">v. 48.</note> and the Romanes will come, and take away our Place and Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Inſinuation, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to conclude their Neceſſity of our Saviour's Death, <hi>Caiphas</hi> addes ſomething, by which he endeavors to prove that Unjuſt Attempt to be not only Neceſſary, but very Plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble too;
<note place="margin">v. 50.</note> and therefore he pleads <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> the <hi>Publick Good</hi> is urged to palliate this execrable Murther: <hi>You,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>know nothing at all, neither conſider that it is expedient one man ſhould dye for the People, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion periſh not:</hi> — as if he had ſaid, You are very Weake and Unskilfull Politicians to boggle at ſuch a Caſe as this, and to debate thus long upon a matter of ſo eaſie ſolution; for Right or Wrong the <hi>Publick Safety</hi> muſt be provided for; and it is a great Folly and want of Foreſight to preferre one man's life, how Innocent ſoever, before a Nations Welfare. In which wicked ſpeech, though <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iphas</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52043:8"/>did by God's appointment Prophetically foretell <hi>that great good which would redound to the World by our Saviour's Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 52.</note> yet as to his own Intention, he meant no more then a Juſtifying of that Accurſed, and,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8.</note> in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul's</hi> ſenſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Damnable</hi> Maxime, viz. <hi>That we may do Evill, that Good may come thereof,</hi> which Tenet, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is aſſented to, will be the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe Miſchiefs which men have either Felt or Feared: I am ſure it ſo far prevailed with that Juncto of Senators, that the Text ſaith <hi>From that Time they took Counſell, how to put him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 53.</note> i. e. our Saviour, <hi>to Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour's Death being thus agreed on by the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and in their deep Policy reſolved to be Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in reſpect of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and very Advantageous too in reference to the <hi>Jewes;</hi> the Contrivers make no long Delay, but what they had before ſo unjuſtly concluded on, we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52043:8"/>find them preſently after as cruelly execute. For having by their own Authority apprehended our Saviour, and being it ſeemes debarred to judg of Capitall Cauſes within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (<hi>it is not,</hi> ſay they to <hi>Pilate,
<note place="margin">v. 32.</note> lawfull for us to put any Man to Death)</hi> they hale him before <hi>Pilate</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Praefect, and there with Loud Clamorous Outcries demand Juſtice againſt him. But leſt their Noiſe ſhould not prevaile with a <hi>Romane,</hi> and therein, ſo far as rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Affaires, an Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and Diſpaſſionate Judge, with a Formall ſtory in their Mouths, diſguiſing the Malice of their Hearts, they Article againſt him as a <hi>Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour,</hi> i. e.
<note place="margin">κακοποιός.</note> according to the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Greek word, <hi>a ſeditious Perſon, a Diſturber of the State,</hi> a <hi>Subverter of Government,</hi> an <hi>Enemy of Ceſar, an Ambitious Affecter to be in Fact, as well as in Title, King of the Jewes;</hi> which Falſe and ſcandalous Charge we have inſinuated by <hi>John,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52043:9"/>but is at large expreſſed by <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ch. 23.2.</note> 
               <hi>we found,</hi> ſay they, <hi>this fellow perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Nation, and forbidding to give Tribute unto Ceſar, ſaying, that he himſelfe is Chriſt a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pilate</hi> hearing this Accuſation, which, if True, ſtrook ſo immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyat <hi>Ceſar's</hi> power; and the Gravity and ſeeming Sanctity of our Saviours Accuſers, would not let him ſuſpect it to be Falſe, he therefore, waving all other ſuggeſtions, haſtily askes our Saviour, whether he was King or not,
<note place="margin">v. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Art thou,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>the King of the Jewes?</hi> To which Queſtion our Saviour returnes an Anſwer in the words I have already alleaged, wherein he intimates that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a <hi>King,</hi> and that he had a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> but that his <hi>Kingdome</hi> was of ſuch a Nature, as <hi>Pilate</hi> need not be Jealous of, nor apprehend any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from it; as if it were intended to enterfere or Juſtle with <hi>Ceſar's</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty; for, ſaith he, <hi>my Kingdome is not of this Word.</hi> As if he had ſaid,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52043:9"/>I am indeed a <hi>King,</hi> and I have a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> but you need not fear any Diſturbance to your Secular Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, by ſetting up of my <hi>Kingdome</hi> amongſt you, for though it be <hi>in the World,</hi> it is not <hi>of the world;</hi> nor hath any Commerce or Society, either with the Power or Policy thereof.</p>
            <p>This being the Plaine and Direct meaning of our Saviour's words, I ſhall briefly explaine what <hi>Kingdome</hi> it is that our Saviour meanes, when he ſaies, <hi>my Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I find in Scripture that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is called a <hi>King</hi> upon a four-fold account,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Power.</hi> Thus he is King of the World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2.</note> and hath a ſover aign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Paramount, being one God with the Father, and the ſame. Power, by which he made the World, he daily exerts for the continuing and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Birth:</hi> thus he was King of the Jewes, being <hi>Heire apparent</hi> to the Crown, and lineally deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52043:10"/>from <hi>David,</hi> in whom the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was veſted with a promiſe of its perpetuity; <hi>from him, according to the fleſh, our Saviour came,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had a Star to adorn and declare his Nativity; God herein ſeeming to comply with the Opinions of thoſe, who think the Heavens are more then ordinarily concerned in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Princes, and therefore ſtrange Appearances, and unuſual Comets do attend both their birth and death, For nothing elſe, for ought we know, but the Prodigy of that Blazing Star (without any more immediate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct) did excite the curioſity of the Eaſtern <hi>Magi,</hi> to go and ſee that Perſon, whoſe Nativity was in ſo wonderful a manner celebrated: <hi>Where is,</hi> ſay they, <hi>he that is born King of the Jews? for we have ſeen his Star in the Eaſt: i.</hi> We have deſcryed a Star of an unuſual Aſpect, but yet ſuch an one, as, according to the rules of our Art, diſcovers that a Prince is born in <hi>Judea,</hi> and we are come
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52043:10"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. To bow to him, and pay him homage.</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig: contr: Celſ: lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 45. Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes their coming to a reſponſe of the Devils, upon their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Rates of Conjuration: but I conceive the opinion, I mention, is more probable.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By <hi>deſignation</hi> and <hi>appointment of his Father:</hi> Thus our Saviour Chriſt is King of all the Heathen, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Propheſie of <hi>Jacob, When Shiloh comes, unto him ſhall</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the obedience or gathering of the Gentiles be:</hi> And many Predictions there are of the ſame importance, which if they are to be meant of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Individual Heathen (and not rather ſignifie that the Heathen ſhall not be excluded from being reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our Saviours ſubjects, now in times of Chriſtianity) we have no ground from Scripture to expect that they ſhall be actually accompliſhed until our Saviours ſecond coming, at which time the Saints ſhall reign with him: Which is the meaning of that promiſe of our Saviours, <hi>He that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes,</hi> i. all difficulties, <hi>and keeps
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52043:11"/>my words unto the end,</hi> i. perſeveres in the Chriſtian Faith, <hi>I will give him power over the Heathen,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>even as I have received of my Father,</hi> i. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, he ſhall reign with me, not in this life, but when he hath exchanged this for a better.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, By <hi>Pact or Covenant:</hi> thus our Saviour is <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Believers</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as a Prince he gives us Laws, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites us with Rewards, deters us by Puniſhments, and hath left nothing unaſſayed, which may either perſwade or enforce obedience; governing of his People by his Word and Spirit, unto a complyance with his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and this Dominion he will always exerciſe to the Worlds end. Of which inward, inviſible Kingdom it is, that our Saviour is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, when he ſaith, <hi>My kingdom is not of this world,</hi> i. not a Political, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and earthly one.</p>
            <p>From all that hath been ſaid, I infer this Concluſion, <hi>That if Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be not of this world, there is none
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52043:11"/>can,
<note place="margin">Theſis.</note> upon the account of their intereſt in Chriſt, plead any Right or Title unto earthly Soveraignty:</hi> or more briefly thus, <hi>That inward Saintſhip is not a ground of outward Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This collection which I make is very eaſie and natural, for if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did diſclaim all earthly Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in himſelf, then ſure none can, upon pretence of their intereſt in him, put in their Plea for it: If our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as he lived an humble, ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, ſo dyed in an utter abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of temporal Soveraignty; and ſpent thoſe few laſt words he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to utter, in a direct denyal of worldly greatneſs: then certainly his example weighs little with us, and his lateſt breath was ſpent in vain, if we, upon a Chriſtian account, ſtill affect Empire, or make our Religion the way to outward preferment. It is our Saviours own reaſoning, and bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the inalterable nature of things, that <hi>the ſervant is not greater then his maſter:</hi> If therefore our <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52043:12"/>would not be called <hi>Lord,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the <hi>ſervants</hi> ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it; if Chriſt refuſed Empire, with what face can <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it? or how can they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Saints,</hi> and yet ſeek to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in power above their <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though the bare authority of our Saviour might alone ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thoſe that are Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (for ſo far as they are ſuch, they are to be imitators of Chriſt) yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter is of ſo much weight, and hath of late been too unhappily diſputed, I ſhall therefore endeavour more at large to demonſtrate it, from theſe two Heads of Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the nature of Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in general.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the nature of Chriſtian Religion in particular.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Saintſhip is not the ground of Soveraignty, appears from the nature of Civil Government in general: for this belongs to men,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52043:12"/>as they are Chriſtians, but as they are men; and is a conſequent, not of our ſpiritual, but of our naturall Birth.</p>
            <p>To clear up this, I ſhall not unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel the whole Myſtery of Policy, as ſome too unwarily, (if not deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly) do, who lay down ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Politicks, as give juſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make their Religion ſuſpected: I ſhall therefore inſiſt onely upon thoſe Grounds which the Scripture affords, onely thoſe being ſufficient to convince a gainſaying, or to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a ſcrupling conſcience. And to begin with the firſt Original of man, we finde, when God made man, it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.28.</note> that <hi>in the Image of God created he him,</hi> and thereupon <hi>bleſſed him, and gave him dominion over the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Now there is a twofold <hi>Image</hi> of God, Supernatural, and Natural: Supernatural, I call thoſe impreſſions of Sanctity and Holineſs, which are now loſt: Natural, is that reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance which the ſoul of man hath to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52043:13"/>the nature of God, as to its being and operation: <hi>viz.</hi> As God is a Spirit Immortal, Inviſible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo the ſoul of man is of a Spirituall, Immortall, Inviſible nature; which Image yet remains entire in the worſt of men: Of this Image it is that God ſpeaks, when he forbids Murther,
<note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood,</hi> s;aith he, <hi>by him ſhall mans blood be ſhed, becauſe in the image of Gad created he man;</hi> i. e. he put a Spirit of life and underſtanding into him, the conſideration of which invaluable Jewel within, ought to make us preſerve the Casket without, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Body, ſacred and inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Which of theſe two Images it is that external Dominion over the Creature belongs to, is clear out of the ſame Chapter, where God renews his grant to all the Sons of <hi>Noah: The fear of you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2.</note> ſaith he, <hi>and the dread of you, fall upon every beaſt of the earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>into your hand, i. e.</hi> power to diſpoſe of as you pleaſe, <hi>are they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52043:13"/>delivered:</hi> In which general grant, there are none of the ſons of men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, becauſe it is a <hi>Birth-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> and profane <hi>Cham</hi> had upon that ſcore as large a ſhare in, and as true a title to the free uſe of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, as any of his more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Brethren.</p>
            <p>This is that Civil Right which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> acknowledged in the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> (and what kinde of abomin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſinners the <hi>Sodomites</hi> were, I need not mention) when he refuſed to be enriched by him; <hi>I will not,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Gen. 14.23</note> 
               <hi>take any thing of thine;</hi> by which word <hi>Thine,</hi> he owns that the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> had a True, Legal Propriety, even in thoſe goods, which <hi>Abraham</hi> might have challenged as the Fruits of his Victory: This Right after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Abraham</hi> confeſſed to be in <hi>Abimelech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.23</note> when he made a League with him not to hurt or injure him, <hi>i.</hi> not to deprive him of any thing which was his. But moſt of all this appears in the bargain and ſale which <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 23.</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52043:14"/>made with the Sons of <hi>Heth;</hi> when <hi>Abraham,</hi> though by Gods ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute grant, the undoubted heir of all the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet the time for the accompliſhment of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe not being yet come, he refuſed to receive the Cave of <hi>Macpelah,</hi> to make uſe of it for a burying place, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he had paid a valuable conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in money for it.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>If any ſhall here object that</hi> Abraham <hi>at that time wanted power to make good his claim, and therefore was content to buy, what otherwiſe he might have forced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The vanity and falſhood (I will adde too, the impiety) of this Plea appears from hence, in that we finde <hi>David</hi> afterwards uſing the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame terms of obſervance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto <hi>Araunah</hi> a <hi>Jebuſite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.</note> one neither of the ſame Nation nor Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with himſelf: Which inſtance ſerves very much to clear the queſtion in hand, for <hi>David</hi> was not onely a Saint by priviledge (if that ſignified
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52043:14"/>any thing to give a right) but a King by power, and might have forced it: nay, he was commanded by God, to make uſe of that very place to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in, and therefore might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended an inſpiration to juſtifie his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent ſeizure; and beſides, to make the matter a little more fair and plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, he, whom <hi>David</hi> dealt with, was an Heathen, and for ought we know, an Idolater: Yet all theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages did not make <hi>David</hi> ſwerve from the Rules of common Juſtice, but up he went with all his Retinue to <hi>Araunah,</hi> in a ſuppliant poſture, that he <hi>might buy his threſhing floor:</hi> And when <hi>Araunah</hi> frankly offered to give it him, the Spirit of God hath recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, not as an act of Juſtice in him, but of Royal Bounty: <hi>Araunah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>as a king, gave unto the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>It uſeth to be urged againſt this, that the</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>which were Gods People, did deſtroy the</hi> Canaanites, <hi>and inherit their Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But the Anſwer is eaſie,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52043:15"/>That as God did not chooſe them to be his people, becauſe they were more holy then others, but meerly becauſe he had ſet his heart upon them. So neither did he give them the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> upon the account of their <hi>Saintſhip,</hi> but onely to make good his promiſe unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> and by their hands to avenge himſelf of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> whoſe iniquitys were then full and ripe for vengeance.</p>
            <p>This reaſon is expreſly given by <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf,
<note place="margin">Deut. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>Not for thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>or for the uprightneſs of thy heart, doeſt thou go to poſſeſs their Land; but for the wickedneſs of theſe nations, the Lord thy God doth drive them out from before thee, and that he may perform the word which the Lord ſware unto thy Fathers.</hi> God indeed is the great Proprietor of all things, but yet he hath given the Earth, without diſtinction, to all the Sons of Men; onely reſerving to himſelf this Right, That when they do ingratefully abuſe his gift, he doth always diſpoſſeſſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52043:15"/>them, and give their inheritance unto others: but though this be the method of Gods Judgements, yet it doth not excuſe any people from a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Crime, who take upon them to be the executors of Gods Decrees againſt the wicked. <hi>Joſhuah</hi> therefore, whileſt he was in the hotteſt purſuit of that promiſed Poſſeſſion, never pleaded any thing to juſtifie his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but the particular command of God, who bad him <hi>go and deſtroy thoſe Nations:</hi> this alone made it a pious War, which otherwiſe would have been nothing elſe but a publick Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery: We finde alſo, that when God, as the ſupream Diſpoſer, gave to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he, at the ſame time, expreſly forbids them to meddle with the Land of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Ammon;</hi> but had relation to God given them any right, that Land would have equally belonged to them with the other:
<note place="margin">Deut. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>When thou comeſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>nigh unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Ammon, <hi>diſtreſs them not,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52043:16"/>nor meddle with them; for I will not give thee of the Land of the children of</hi> Ammon <hi>any poſſeſsion, becauſe I have given it unto the children of</hi> Lot <hi>for a poſſeſsion.</hi> Where we ſee the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Lot,</hi> though Idolatrous, yet were not to be diſturbed in their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, becauſe the ſame God who ſaid to the children of <hi>Iſrael, Goe, Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe Canaan,</hi> ſaid to the Children of <hi>Lot, Goe, Poſſeſs the Land of Ammon.</hi> Whereby, as to their civil Claims, and temporal Rights, God makes no diſtinction betwixt the one, though his own peculiar, and the other, though a profane and Idolatrous people.</p>
            <p>But if Heathen unregenerate men have, upon the account of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, a Title to other things, then certainly to Dominion much more; which ſerves onely to ſecure our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Priviledges, and is, if rightly ſtated, nothing elſe but a conſequent of Propriety.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore conclude this firſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52043:16"/>Argument, which I think abundantly convincing, with that remarkable Controverſie between God and the Jews, concerning their obedience to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi> The Jews, though undoubted poſſeſſors of <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet after they were by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> conquered, and, to preſerve ſome little remains of Liberty and Lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, had taken an Oath of Fealty and Allegiance to him; we finde, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome reaſon of State, they were preſently induced to break it, and God as ſpeedily threatens to avenge it ſeverely upon them.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 17.</note> The ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of that Oath, how it was a Covenant only to enſlave themſelves and their Poſterity for ever, God himſelf doth declare, thereby to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their Objection:
<note place="margin">v 13 14.</note> 
               <hi>The King of Babylon,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hath taken of the Kings ſeed,</hi> i. Zedekiah, <hi>and made a Covenant with him, and taken an oath of him, that the Kingdom might be baſe, that it might not lift it ſelf up, i. e.</hi> that it might for ever quit the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52043:17"/>pretence of being a <hi>Free People,</hi> and truckle under the Dominion of the <hi>Chaldeans:</hi> This Yoke, then which nothing can be more inſupportable, and to which the Jews had been ſo long unaccuſtomed, they preſently ſhook off; for it follows in the next Verſe, <hi>But he,</hi> i. Zedekiah, <hi>rebelled,</hi> with what ſucceſs, we have too much reaſon in this Nation to read and tremble
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Plea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> v. 18, 19.</note>: <hi>Seeing he deſpiſed the oath, by breaking the Covenant, when loe, he had given his hand (i.</hi> with hands lifted up, had ſolemnly ratified it) <hi>he ſhall not eſcape: Therefore, as I live, ſaith the Lord, my Covenant which he hath broken, and my Oath which he hath deſpiſed, will I recompenſe upon his own head:</hi> From which ſad place, others perhaps will draw other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, but I ſhall collect onely theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in every Oath God is a Party, and will be ſure to puniſh the violater of it; though men may break their Oathes, with as much eaſe as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52043:17"/>
               <hi>Samſon</hi> did his <hi>Withs,</hi> yet God will be ſure to keep his, and he hath ſworn to Puniſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When once a man hath ſworne, he cannot reſume againe that naturall Liberty, which he was before poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, becauſe by his owne voluntary Act he hath deveſted himſelfe of it, and thereby bound himſelfe over to Divine vengeance, if he do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Condition of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if the Jewes, who had ſo much to plead for themſelves, both upon a Civil and Religious Account, as being not onely a Free, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Godly People, might yet paſſe away their whole Liberty unto an Heathen Prince, and by vertue of their Oath be debarred for ever from forceable ſeeking a Re-enveſtiture; but were obliged, not onely to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto him as their Conquerour, but after Faith given, to obey him as their Soveraigne; if I ſay, the Caſe ſtood thus with them, then certainly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52043:18"/>no Pretence of Sanctitie can abſolve us now from ſuch Ties of Obedience, in the Times of the Goſpell; which doth as farre tranſcend the Jewiſh Politie in Peaceableneſſe of Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in Purity of Doctrine, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg: </seg>2</label> Secondly, that Saintſhip is not the ground of Soveraignty will yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeare from the Nature of Chriſtian Religion in particular, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we reſpect, 1. Its Precepts. 2. Its Promiſes. 3. The manner of propagating it. 4. The Practiſe of the Apoſtles, and other Profeſſours in the pureſt and moſt Primitive Times.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This appeares from Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell Precepts: for there is nothing more frequently or vehemently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by our Saviour, then <hi>ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall.</hi> The command doth not run, <hi>Take a Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat: 16.24</note> but, <hi>Take up your Croſse and follow me. Learne of me,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, he doth not adde, For this is the way to Honour, for I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52043:18"/>can point you out a Path to Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but <hi>Learn of me,
<note place="margin">Mat: 11.26</note> for I am mecke and Lowly.</hi> i. I have equalled my ſelfe to the meaneſt of the ſons of men, I have not where to lay my head, and am ſo little deſirous of worldly Greatneſs, that I have vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily deveſted my ſelfe of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Royalty, then the world can comprehend; and all this I have done, to ſhow you a Patterne of Humility. Therefore when the Diſciple, (who before our Saviours Reſurrection, did as much miſtake the meaning of his Kingdome, as ſome amongſt us now do) did contend amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves who ſhould be greateſt, how ſharply doth our Saviour reprehend this Ambitious ſtrife?
<note place="margin">Mat: 18.3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>If you be not turned,</hi> i. quite chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as it were, into another Nature, and <hi>become as little Children,</hi> as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and ſecure of greatneſs, as little ſwelled and leavened with Ambition, <hi>you ſhall in no wiſe enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven:</hi> whereby the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52043:19"/>of Heaven:</hi> whether we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Grace or Glory, whether it meanes Initiall or Compleat Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is all one to the Queſtion in hand, for it clearly proves, that to affect Temporall Greatneſſe and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, is utterly inconſiſtent either with holineſſe here, or with our hopes hereafter. I need not multiply more Texts, for the whole deſigne of the Goſpell is aimed at nothing elſe, but to levell, and lower our Thoughts unto the ſize of our Saviours meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to beat down the tumour and ſwelling, and agitation of our Spirits in reference to worldly things, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty and deveſt our ſoules of all that wind of Ambition, wherewith poore miſerable men, who have no better Hopes, are conſtantly toſſed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed. And the reaſon for this is unanſwerable, for, if, as our Saviour hath ſtated it, <hi>None can ſerve God and Mammon,</hi> then none can ſerve God &amp; Honour, we cannot ſerve God, and gaine a Kingdome; much leſſe are we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52043:19"/>to make one, prepare the way for the other: for this would be to invert the Intent of the Goſpell, and make it a ſetter up of what it was principally diſcovered to beat downe; whereby it would become nothing elſe, but a Ladder for Ambition to climbe by.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This appeares likewiſe from Goſpell Promiſes; for theſe as they are conſtantly annexed to the Poore, the Humble, the Mortified, the ſelfe denying Chriſtian, ſo they are alwayes about ſuch things, as are moſt remote and diſtant from Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Enjoyments <hi>Bleſsed,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>are the poore in ſpirit,</hi> he doth not adde,
<note place="margin">Muth. 5.</note> for theirs ſhall be the Kingdome of Earth, but, <hi>Theirs is the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Analogie of which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, muſt that Text be underſtood, which while they fixe onely upon the Literall meaning, hath deluded ſo many, <hi>Bleſſed are the Meek, for they ſhall Inherit the Earth.</hi> i. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>illam Terram, That Earth,</hi> which was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52043:20"/>promiſed in a Type, and is Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively Heaven, as the Author to the Hebrewes hath elegantly proved. For that neither that place,
<note place="margin">Heb: 11.13 16.</note> nor any other in the N. T. can be underſtood abſolutely of any outward and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Happineſſe, is cleare, becauſe all that we Chriſtians can certainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in this world, by virtue of a Promiſe,
<note place="margin">Joh: 16.33</note> is onely Afflictions. <hi>In the VVorld,</hi> ſaith our Saviour to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and therein to all who will be like them, <hi>you ſhall have Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> this was the laſt Legacy he left them,
<note place="margin">2 Tim: 3.12</note> and therefore, ſaith he, <hi>ye ſhall have it,</hi> reſt ye as certaine of it, as of your Inheritance or Patrimony. And the Apoſtle, who very well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood our Saviour's meaning, laies it down as a Fundamentall in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>All that will live Godly in Chriſt, muſt ſuffer Perſecution;</hi> they muſt ſuffer, there is no avoiding it. For this Fatall attendance of Perſecution upon Piety it is, that our Saviour hath provided us ſo many Cordialls
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52043:20"/>and Comfortable <hi>Receipts</hi> in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as when he bids us <hi>to rejoice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat: 5. &amp;c. Heb. 12.</note> and <hi>be exceeding glad:</hi> nay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to skip and dance for Joy,</hi> when ſuch Afflictions do moſt beſet us; for they are evidences of our Sonſhip, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ſignes that God hath a Care of us: all which Expreſſions would have been very vaine and uſeleſſe, if ever Religion ſhould be abuſed to thoſe Ends, that the ſuffering might become the Afflicting Party; if a Chriſtian could not only exempt himſelfe from Injuries, but returne them upon others, and challenge Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority here, as a Reward of his Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For this would not only deprive us of the Priviledge (ſo the Apoſtles counted it) of Martyrdome, but would have none fit to be Perſecuted, but onely the Wicked; and this is an Honour, which I hope no true Chriſtian but envies them. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of grace,
<note place="margin">Phil: 1.15</note> not only to believe on Chriſt, but likewiſe to ſuffer for his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52043:21"/>Name.</hi> We are miſtaken, whilſt we ſo much dread Affliction: for it is not a Judgment, no nor an Evill neither to ſuffer, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Gift,</hi> a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Boone, a choice Indulgence of God unto his Favourites. So the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> bids thoſe he writes to not be diſcouraged, or <hi>count it ſtrange,</hi> if the <hi>Fiery Tryall</hi> had its effect upon them,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 11.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as well as upon others; <hi>for,</hi> faith he, <hi>unto this were ye called:</hi> as if he had ſaid, be ſure you look, nay long for it; for if you miſſe of this, you have ſome reaſon to doubt the Truth of your <hi>Calling.</hi> All which places, with many more to the ſame purpoſe, how any can reconcile to an Affecting of Temporall Greatneſſe, let them reſolve who love a Secure, an Eaſie, a Specious, a Proſperous Religion, ſuch an one as Chriſt never came to teach, nor any of his Followers died to eſtabliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It is very true, what ſome, with a little too much guſt and reliſh of worldly-mindedneſs, alledge, That
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52043:21"/>every true Chriſtian is heir of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ought to live in expectation of ſuch Glory and Greatneſs, as what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the world hath, can but imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſhadow out: With this our Saviour doth buoy up, and revive the ſinking ſpirits of his Diſciples: <hi>Be of good comfort,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for it is your Fathers good pleaſure to give you a Kingdom:</hi> It is this we pray for, this we are to be in a readineſs for daily.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But yet it is as true too, that, ſo long as we live here, this is a Kingdom in expectation onely; Fleſh nor Blood, neither ſhall nor can inherit it. As we muſt firſt put off Mortality, before we can put on E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life; ſo we muſt put off earth and earthly-mindedneſs, before we can expect any ſhare in that bleſſed Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
            <p>There are, amongſt many other, two very remarkable places to clear this: The one is our Saviours anſwer to <hi>Peter,</hi> upon his Diſcourſe with the <hi>young man:</hi> For our Saviour having
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52043:22"/>pronounced ſo ſevere, and yet ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory a doom againſt rich men, as that a <hi>rich man could ſcarcely be ſaved;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he repeats it again, and makes it to be altogether as great a Moral Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, for a man that is clogged with Wealth, and loaded with worldly Cares, <hi>to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> (that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, preſſed, and ſtreightned way</hi>) as it would be a natural impoſſibility for a <hi>Camel to go through the eye of a needle.</hi> Upon this we finde the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples were exceedingly amazed, not onely as miſſing of their hopes, but likewiſe as being conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that though they were not, yet they did all deſire to be rich; whereupon <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of the reſt, replies, <hi>Behold, we have left all and followed thee, what ſhall we have therefore?</hi> As if he had ſaid, Shall we venture to looſe all, and yet be ſo great loſers by the bargain, as to be altogether unprovided of a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence? our Saviour therefore to quit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52043:22"/>them, and to take them off from ſuch ſenſual deſires, which he ſaw poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them: <hi>Verily,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ye that have followed me, in the regeneration, when the Son of man ſits upon his Throne of Glory, ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael:</hi> In which words our Saviour doth promiſe them a great and a glorious reward, <hi>viz.</hi> to be Kings and Judges with himſelf, but yet defers the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, until the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. <hi>The reſtauration of all things,</hi> when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mortality nor Miſery ſhall be any more, but every thing ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto that Primitive Integrity and Luſtre, wherein they were at firſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated.</p>
            <p>The other place which manifeſts the nature of Chriſts Kingdom,
<note place="margin">Matth. 20.20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> is that Anſwer which our Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> Children, who, it ſeems, miſtaking the true notion of it, and fixing her thoughts upon an earthly Empire, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned our Saviour for her two ſons,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52043:23"/>
               <hi>That the one might ſit at his right hand, and the other at his left, when he came into his Kingdom, i.</hi> when he had taken poſſeſſion of the Throne, and was inveſted with the Realm of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> ſhe humbly begged, that then he would be pleaſed to look favor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably upon her two ſons, to make them the <hi>Grandees</hi> and <hi>Minions</hi> of his Court; that they, under him, might enjoy the greateſt Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: But our Saviour, to take them off from ſuch haughty Aims, preſently puts them in minde of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 23.</note> as a thing much more ſuited to a Chriſtians complexion; and leſt the other Diſciples ſhould be infected with the ſame deſires, he doth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtrive to ſuppreſs them, as paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons much more fit for Heathen, then Chriſtian tempers: <hi>Ye know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the Princes of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles do exerciſe dominion over them, and thoſe that are great, do exerciſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon them: But it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you:</hi> As if he had ſaid,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52043:23"/>The Heathen indeed, who have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope, do place all their Heaven upon Earth; they make Fame their Immortality, and Power their Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; and therefore never reſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, until they can exerciſe an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and an Arbitrary Dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their enſlaved Subjects. But you, who are my Diſciples, and called by my Name, who have a certainty of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Enjoyments, unto whom a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a clean different nature is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; you ought not to be like them, but rather ſtrive in humility to excell each other: Wherein our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our clearly intimates, that it doth ſo little become a <hi>Saint</hi> to rule, that he is certainly not a <hi>Saint</hi> who doth am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition it: For how can he rationally expect a Kingdom hereafter, who hath outed himſelf of his Plea, by putting in for a Kingdom here? which is nothing elſe, but to antedate the effect of Gods promiſe; or rather with <hi>Dives,</hi> to receive our good things in this life, and to take up with Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52043:24"/>Joys, when we ſhould patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have waited for Eternal.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This appears farther, from the manner how Chriſtian Religion was propagated in the World, which, as it is a Religion that doth moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely forbid compulſion and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſo it was not planted by it. Our Saviour himſelf that taught it, was <hi>as a Lamb that opened not his mouth, but turned his cheek to the ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and his back to the rod of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked:</hi> The Apoſtles, his followers, were accounted the ſcum and off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, <hi>i.</hi> the vileſt of men, and thereupon were diſgraced, perſecuted, tormented: And all this they ſuffered without the return, ſo much as of contumelious Language; how much leſs do we finde them tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the world, that they ought to bear Dominion over them: Yet by theſe Arts alone, they did at firſt Preach, and afterwards promote the Goſpel to the converſion of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. And this, by the way, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52043:24"/>any further Argument, will ſerve to evidence the Divine Original of Chriſtianity, in that notwithſtanding all theſe diſadvantages, the leaſt of which, in all humane probality, was enough to have ſtifled and ſuppreſſed it in the Womb; yet, in ſpite of all, it took root and proſpered; which could not poſſibly have come to paſs, without the conduct and aſſiſtance of an Almighty Power.</p>
            <p>But had our Saviour ſent a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the World, which would have excited mens ambition, and fired our Zeal to the ruine and extirpation of it's Oppoſers: <hi>Quid hoc eximium?</hi> What excellence ſhould there have been in Chriſtian Religion, more then in other Religions? for do not even the Publicans the ſame? Is not this the common method of all Political Combinations, rather then Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the World, to riſe by the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of ſuch as oppoſe them? But our Saviour took not this courſe: <hi>If,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 18.27.</note> ſaith he, <hi>my kingdom were of this world,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52043:25"/>then would my ſervants fight?</hi> intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that to make way for Religion by force, to lay down a Principle, which muſt needs imbroil the World in Blood and Confuſion, is not Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but Rapine; a Sacrilegious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, to make Chriſtianity, &amp; the ſtrict Profeſſors of it, odious: For who will not ſuſpect the truth of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which deſpairing of its own Excellence, and hopeleſs of a better reward, eggs on its followers to take up with Worldly Honor? and under the notion of Sanctity, leaves the Throne expoſed to the Invaſion of every Hypocritical Pretender: <hi>At in initio non fuit ſic?</hi> Our Saviour taught us no ſuch Doctrine, nor did his Apoſtles leave us ſuch a patern. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That Saintſhip gives no right to Civil Empires appears from the practice of the Apoſtles, and other Profeſſors of Chriſtianity in the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and moſt Primitive Times. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after our Saviours Aſcenſion,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52043:25"/>when by <hi>Peters</hi> Miniſtry ſo many thouſands were converted; we doe not finde him Preaching them into a Tumult, or raiſing a Party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People, upon the ſcore of our Saviours being a Temporall Prince, to whom all men were to pay their Civill Allegeance, but he onely bids them,
<note place="margin">Act. 111.29.</note> 
               <hi>Repent and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, that their ſins might be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out:</hi> And ſuch Doctrine as this might be Preached, without any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment to <hi>Caeſars</hi> Power.</p>
            <p>Again, when the <hi>chief Prieſts and Rulers</hi> did forbid the Apoſtles to Preach in the Name of Chriſt; as being madded with envy, that one whom they had lately ſo ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Crucified, ſhould yet finde ſo much reputation among his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: The Apoſtles, upon this, doe not combine to ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and, under pretence of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Chriſts Kingdom, make a commotion in the State, but they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52043:26"/>preſently fell to their Prayers,
<note place="margin">Act. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>Now Lord,</hi> ſay they, <hi>behold their threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and grant unto thy ſervants, that with all boldneſs they may ſpeak thy Word.</hi> They onely beg cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to ſpeak, and patience to ſuffer, and as for promoting Chriſts Throne in any other ſenſe, they ſeem altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecure and careleſs.</p>
            <p>As the Apoſtles, ſo did their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes behave themſelves, ſo farre from aiming at greatneſſe, or from ſeeking to improve their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the oppreſſion of others; ſo farre from depriving others of their Poſſeſſions, becauſe they were ungodly, that they ſold their own, and therein literally fulfilled that command of our Saviour, of <hi>Sell all and follow me;</hi> which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of our Times, are ſo farre from practiſing, that they are rather apt to do the clean contrary.</p>
            <p>We reade indeed, that when the Chriſtians increaſed, there was an
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52043:26"/>Accuſation forged againſt them,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.6.</note> as if they were <hi>Men, who turned the World upſide down, who acted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Decrees of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, There is another King, one Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> is by <hi>Tertullus</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a very Peſt,</hi> i.
<note place="margin">Act 24.</note> a Turbulent, Unquiet Spirited man, and a <hi>Raiſer of Sedition;</hi> which Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, how falſe and ungrounded it was, <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews at large in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, by averring to their faces, that <hi>they could not prove the things which they had alleaged againſt him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 13.</note> And afterwards, he is fully acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Feſtus</hi> the Roman Deputy: <hi>They,</hi> ſayes he to Agrippa, <hi>brought againſt him no Accuſation of ſuch things as I ſuppoſed, i.</hi> of Treaſon,
<note place="margin">Act. 25.8.</note> of Sedition or Rebellion, of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſobedience, or non-payment of Tribute to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> for ſuch crimes as theſe, were properly under the Governors Cognizance; and none of theſe, it ſeems, were ſo much
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52043:27"/>as imputed unto <hi>Paul:</hi> whereas had he ſo Preached up Chriſt, as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that Jeſus was not onely a King, but that whoever did not ſubmit to him, ought immediately to be put out of Office; whereby there would never be ſuch a Crime as Treaſon, if Religion were once made the pretence to juſtifie it. Had this, I ſay, been <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine, I ſuppoſe <hi>Feſtus</hi> neither would, nor durſt have been ſo favorable in his Cenſure.</p>
            <p>And to put the matter out of queſtion on that Apoſtles part, though none was more zealous then he, for the advancing of Chriſts Kingdom in the right-ſenſe; yet none was more ſtrict and ſevere in the enjoyning of Obedience unto all Powers over us, of what Religion ſoever; unleſſe we think men can be worſe then <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Caligula</hi> were, who Raigned about his time. And the Apoſtle gives a reaſon for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52043:27"/>it, which will hold true in all Ages,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe, <hi>Authority is from God.</hi> Power, by what Arts ſoever it is gained, and by what perſons ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it is exerciſed, yet when it is once acknowledged and ſworn too, it is to be looked upon by us, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Ray of Gods So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, and therefore to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Sacred. Nor can any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of zeal, or mask of Religion, juſtifie Rebellion more now then heretofore: but the more piety ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to diſguiſe it, the more mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous it is: Since in effect it onely ſets up Chriſt againſt himſelf, and makes his Kingdom what he would not have it to be, <hi>a kingdome of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very ſame command, and to the ſame purpoſe is enforced by <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 11.12.</note> That they might by their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and meekneſſe, put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, who cenſured them as evil doers:</hi> The Word in the Original is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52043:28"/>very ſame which was charged upon our Saviour, and it ſignifies in the <hi>Helleniſtical</hi> Phraſe, <hi>State-Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries, Incompatible with Civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and the like; which would have proved a very true and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right cenſure, in caſe the Chriſtians of thoſe Times, had ſo owned <hi>Chriſt</hi> for their <hi>King,</hi> as, upon his account, to withdraw their obedience from their Civil Soveraigns. The more apt therefore profane men were to miſ-interpret the Kingdom of Chriſt, the more carefull that Apoſtle would have Profeſſors to be, not to give any ſuch occaſion of offence.</p>
            <p>Suitable to the Doctrine of theſe two great Apoſtles, was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Primitive Chriſtians, down from our Saviours, till long after <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, as I could eaſily prove out of the moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Records,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tertul. Apulog: Orig: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Celſ. &amp;c.</note> but that we live in an Age, when ſuch kinde of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, by thoſe who leaſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52043:28"/>it, accounted little leſſe then madneſſe; and that we may know which way the World is going, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance begins once more to be the Mother of Devotion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore draw to a cloſe, for ſuch as Scripture will not ſatisfie, I do not intend to confute by humane Teſtimony, which is not onely falli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but for the moſt part falſe: And I wiſh all that are at leaſure to peruſe this ſhort Treatiſe, would make this uſe of it, as to look after the Spirit, rather then the Splendor of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity: For it is evident to all, that know any thing of Church Story, that ſo much as our Religion hath got in Pomp, it always loſt in Purity.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are ſtill doting upon Chriſts temporal Reign, in which they hope to have their ſhare; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the very ambition of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, ſhould convince them that they are not Chriſtian; but if they are ſo far gone in their Error, as to think nothing unlawful, ſo they may in their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52043:29"/>ſenſe ſet up Chriſt; I heartily wiſh them to conſider, whileſt they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſuch enterprizes, 1. Whoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs they do not. 2. Whoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they doe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Let them conſider whoſe buſineſſe they doe not; for, let them pretend what they will, they doe not the buſineſſe of Chriſt, ſince he hath abſolutely forbid it; and he will not thank us for exalting his Honor the wrong way: <hi>Quis requiſivit haec?</hi> was Gods expoſtulation with the Jews, when they brought him Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, which he himſelf had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, becauſe they offered them not in a right manner. How much more will our Saviour by theſe words, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all thoſe, who for his ſake, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon actions which he at his death diſclaimed? The queſtion at the laſt day will not be, how many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked we have killed, but how many we have converted? Not, how many we have deſtroyed for their unbelief, but how many we have turned from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52043:29"/>it: We ſhall not be asked, what Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Preferments we have got by the Goſpel, but what we have left to follow it: And don't let any think, as ſome argue, that God hath allowed a diſpenſation for theſe laſt times; for times, and men, may alter, but the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things can never alter: Since the world is as inticing, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel as ſevere as ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying, now as ever: ſo that to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe two together, <hi>viz.</hi> the pride of Life, with the Purity of Faith, I think no man can, I am ſure no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to doe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As they who are otherwiſe minded, do not the buſineſs of Chriſt, ſo let them conſider whoſe buſineſſe they do. To underſtand which, we muſt take notice there are in Scripture recorded, two great Pretenders unto temporal Soveraignty, <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Satan:</hi> we finde him directly claiming the glory of the world as his own: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he to our Savior
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52043:30"/>
               <hi>all this power will I give thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>and the glory of them; for that is delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and to whomſoever I will, I give it:</hi> Which confident ſpeech of his, as our Saviour doth not confute, ſo, by calling him after,
<note place="margin">John 16.</note> 
               <hi>the God and Prince of this world,</hi> he ſeems to own it for a truth. And indeed, if we conſider the manner, how; the Arts, by which the Kingdoms of the world are got and governed, we ſhall not much doubt of Satans veracity: Since Fraud and force, are thoſe two Pillars, upon w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> almoſt all Empire is founded; and the great Maxime in State Policy, is that thing which God moſt abhors, <hi>viz.</hi> Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation. So that we need not much queſtion, but as the <hi>wiſdom</hi> or <hi>policy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ja: 11.15.</note> ſo likewiſe the <hi>power of the world,</hi> is not onely <hi>earthly</hi> and <hi>ſenſual,</hi> but likewiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh;</hi> and ſo much the more Deviliſh, the more Religion is prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to procure it; for Satan never more acts his part, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he becoms an <hi>angel of light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Another pretence to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52043:30"/>worldly power diſcovered unto us in Scripture, is <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> of whom there are ſo many Marks and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters given us, that it is no hard matter to know where his ſpirit works: Of him the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, when having diſcourſed, that <hi>whatever is in the world,</hi> whether <hi>the luſt of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 2.16.</note> i. Pleaſure; <hi>or the luſt of the eyes,</hi> i. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; or <hi>the pride of life,</hi> i. Honor, <hi>it was not of the Father, but of the world;</hi> he preſently tells them that Antichriſt was then beginning, intimating, that when ever he came to appear more manifeſtly, he would be very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and remarkable for the ſetting up thoſe three, which are, as one calls them, <hi>The worlds Trinity:</hi> And this he would do, not in ſo open and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced a manner as Satan before him, but under the diſguiſe and mask of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; for thus it is ſaid in the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of him, which all ſides agree to be meant of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.11</note> that <hi>he had horns like a lamb, but he ſpake as a dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> i. he pretended meekneſs, but pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52043:31"/>cruelty; as appears afterwards, in that he is ſaid to force his Religion upon others, and to make all men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his mark,
<note place="margin">ver. 16, 17.</note> or quit their means of living. And there are two Notes of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which will never fail, <hi>viz.</hi> Pride in himſelf, and Perſecution in reference to others.</p>
            <p>Another deſcription we have of him, in that ſtile he aſſumes to himſelf, <hi>viz. That he exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or worſhipped:</hi> The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that he challenges authority and pre-eminence above all Kings and Emperors: For Kings, in Scripture, are called Gods; and Σέβασμο (which we render, <hi>that is worſhipped</hi>) is that name in Greek, which ſignifies <hi>Majeſty</hi> in Engliſh, and is the title by which they did expreſs the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperors, whom they called <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſti,</hi> and the <hi>Greeks</hi> Σέβασοί. According to this aſpiring diſpoſition and nature in him, ſo hath he his name of Anti-Chriſt given him; for Αντιχριςος may either be rendred Αντι <hi>pro,</hi> or <hi>vice Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52043:31"/>that is, one who places himſelf in Chriſts ſtead, and behaves himſelf as his <hi>Vicar</hi> and <hi>Deputy:</hi> Or elſe Αντι may ſignifie <hi>contra Chriſtum,</hi> one that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and ſets himſelf againſt Chriſt, <hi>i.</hi> not againſt his Perſon (for that he would get nothing by) but againſt the principal parts of Chriſts Doctrine and Worſhip; one that puts Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity upon a new bottom, that inverts the deſign of it, and makes it, inſtead of being a <hi>ſelf-denying,</hi> the moſt ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeking Religion in the World.</p>
            <p>How near this Doctrine of making Chriſts Kingdom an Earthly Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, comes to the nature of Anti-Chriſt; nay, is indeed that very ladder by which that <hi>man of ſin</hi> either alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath, or hereafter will aſcend the Throne, is too apparent: For if Anti-Chriſt be come, as who can now doubt of it? (ſince the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>that in the latter time he needs muſt come;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, <hi>that the latter time began in his age</hi>) then we have no Character left
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52043:32"/>to deſcry him by, if this be not it, <hi>viz.</hi> his mixing the Chriſtian with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt; his making Piety a Pandar to Policy; his advancing Chriſt in ſhew, that thereby indeed he may advance himſelf; his centring god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and greatneſs in the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and ruling over the world as the Deputy of Chriſt: Which kinde of Doctrine whoever attempts to vent, let his zeal be never ſo fierce, and his pretences never ſo pious, he doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but prepare the way for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, whoſe coming will not be like our Saviours, <hi>lowly and meck,</hi> but with pomp and triumph. He doth not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel the ways and ſuppreſs ambition, but ſwell it higher, until he ſinks down Religion under the weight of worldly Honor.</p>
            <p>Before therefore I doe conclude this Diſcourſe, I ſhall take leave,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To bewail many of my deluded Brethren, who have a zeal, but ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, according to knowledge, that even then when they moſt fiercely oppoſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52043:32"/>Antichriſt, they onely do his work; and while they proceed upon falſe Principles, juſt draw a Circle, in which, the more they labor to go from the point they fixed on at firſt, the nearer they draw unto it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I muſt lament the great ſtupor and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility of the Preachers of the Goſpel in our days, who can be ſo careleſs in times of ſo eminent danger: And though others may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps plead ſomething in their own excuſe, yet how can they anſwer it, who ſcrupled at Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies (which were declared, and every one knows to be, in their own nature, indifferent) and yet are ſilent under a Principle which will certainly bring them back, in a far other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then they were at firſt impoſed? ſhal thoſe who were affrighted at the ſhadow of a Lyon, not tremble to hear him roaring? what folly is it to flee from the tail of the Dragon, and yet not be afraid when we perceive his ſting? Let us not be miſtaken, it is not the garb or dreſs of Ceremonies, it is not this or that form of Worſhip, which preſently makes it Antichriſtian, but it is the challenging a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to impoſe them upon others. So that without fixing the name of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> upon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52043:33"/>any party of men, which makes the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie conjectural onely, and moſt commonly uncharitable; this I ſhall be bold to affirm, that to impoſe by force any form of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and thereby deny others that liberty of choice, which, whilſt we impoſe, we aſſume to our ſelves: To determine the indifferency of things, and, in reference to Religious ends, to make that neceſſary, which by nature was made, and God hath left free: And above all, to make Chriſt a temporal Prince, and under the notion of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him, to exalt our ſelves, and Lord it over others; this is nothing elſe but the ſpirit of Antichriſt, ſince ſuch Doctrine as this, is no way contained in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak out and end; I earneſtly pray, that that excellent Principle, I mean, <hi>Liberty of conſcience,</hi> which firſt led us out of Popery, doe not by our too wanton abuſe of it, lead us back again into it. This I am ſure of, that for men firſt to call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>The Godly,</hi> (a ſtile which <hi>Paul,</hi> after all his Revelations, did not ſo boldly aſſume) and then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſcore, to make themſelves our Governors, is without any ſtreining the road thither; for we know who it is, that by ſuch Arts, hath got no ſmall Dominion in the world: and where ever ſuch Tenets prevail, they are onely fore-runners of Antichriſts Temporal regin, and ſo far as he can ſuppreſs it, of Chriſtianities ruine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52043:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
